[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, the sutta for today, well, the two suttas, actually, it's Yūtanikā 4524 and then the other one will be Anguttara 557.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, this one's very short, it says,
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha was addressing the bhikkhus and he said, bhikkhus, whether for a lay person or for one gone forth, I do not praise the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it is a lay person or one gone forth, who is practicing wrongly because of an undertaking the wrong way of practice, he does not attain the method, the dhamma, that is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he does not develop the right view, he does not become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what because is the wrong way?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the wrong view, wrong intention, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong leg collection and wrong composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is called the wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whether it's a layperson or one gone forth who is practicing wrongly, that is basically the reason that their practice does not lead to the attainment of the method and to the dhamma that is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, because whether a lay person or or a monk, I praise the right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's a lay person or one going forth who is practicing rightly, because they undertake the right way of practice and they attain the method, the dhamma that is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: What because is the right way, it's the right view, right intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right recollection, right composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's called the right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought just to kind of have this, add this sutta just as a reminder.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think even people who have been listening to our talks, even like regularly or over a longer period of time, I think even they would, some of them, might still have a certain
[SPEAKER_00]: There are kind of tacit assumptions and notions that the practice can be done differently if you're a householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you can't ordain for whatever reason, you might feel like, well, you know, I just can't help but be excused from certain requirements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this sutta just cuts through all of that and says it's simply not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and I think also, like, often what happens, you know, the five precepts, the eight precepts, the celibacy or the kind of non-celibacy, the lines get blurred and then... and also thanks to the, like, contemporary Theravāda not making it any clearer and kind of confounding the matter further,
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people would even, like, read this sutra, which clearly talks about the Noble Eightfold Path, that it's the same for monks and lay people, without the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It constitutes the right way or the wrong way, but they would still kind of believe, well, you know, I don't have to do it to such an extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, I can get away without being celibate, or I can get away with with my speech, you know, sometimes being kind of unwholesome, because that's just the world we live in, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, again, nobody forces you to follow the Noble Eightfold Path, or try to, or not, but if your goal is to practice the dhamma, then there is no other way around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, when the Buddha lists the... What constitutes the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_00]: the right view, which we often talk about, you know, understanding where the suffering comes from, the Four Noble Truths, there are many different ways you could sort of... many different aspects you could use to describe it, but it kind of leads to the same understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right recollection, right composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, right intention, like, right thought, right intention, was always defined as intention of non-sensuality, intention of non-ill-will and non-cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Consequently, that means that the wrong intention is the intention of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if one is not practicing the right intention, one is away from the path.
[SPEAKER_00]: One will not be able to attain the method, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just to illustrate a point where people think like, oh, I can...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to be celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I can still practice the dhamma in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, if you're not... like, if you cannot physically withdraw yourself from sensuality, mentally will be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be inconceivable for you to be able to mentally not have a sensual intention, if you are still physically engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said many times, you know, the simile of the sticks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if the sticks are still floating in the river, well, no amount of your knowledge of how to light the fire can make any difference, because they're simply soaking wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to take them out of the river first, but even then, you gotta wait for them to dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's this part of drying up, like, your bodily behavior that you would have stopped.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you have to dry up your mind in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, like, this work that applies on the level of right thoughts, right intentions, right images, as we mentioned in our other talks on the channel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole training, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you wear the robes or not, if you want to practice the dhamma, you have to follow the same path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, usually, the difference that the suttas kind of describe between the lay people that practice the dhamma and the monks was not in how they practiced, was not in how they got to there.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a matter of fact, there is not a single sutta that describes a lay person's method of practice independent of talking to the Buddha, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, they're like, oh, the Buddha said this is how lay people should practice towards Sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_00]: No such thing exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suttas exist like this, where there is no differentiation between the method, and then the suttas exist of after they became Sotāpanna and noble disciples, and kind of what they returned to, or what they chose to do, whether to ordain, whether to pursue it further, or they were content with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, like, the the the method of getting there is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: According to the suttas, it would make no sense to... for lay people that the method would... that the requirement for the method is lower than for the monks, because monks would have already be given up the the lay life, the attachments, the safety of family, which means surely then there would be less requirements for the monk's practice and more for lay person's practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people today like to believe the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the method was the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was not the same was after
[SPEAKER_00]: You get the right view after you attain the math, after you understand the nature of suffering, after there is no second arrow hitting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you content with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you choose to stop there, and then, okay, I'll go back.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not have left family, but you would have certainly been internally withdrawn from it, in terms of practicing the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might choose to go back, and support, and then look after people that depend on you, or for whatever reason, or maybe your health prevents you to live like a monastic life, or so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you would know that that's now not the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know exactly what practice was undertaken to get you to that method, to that understanding of the dhamma that is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, for many people, that might feel like more than enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, in a way, it kind of is, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, it's still like... it's a major leap.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bigger leap from a puthujjana to a sotāpāna than from a sotāpāna to a sakadāgāmī, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was understandable that even in the suttas, the Buddha had to go around kind of prodding and sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: There is still work to be done, and you'll regret it later, because this stood now, in your life, this life in particular,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the most optimal.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the amount of effort that you make in this life towards the dhamma practice has the highest benefit, has the highest gain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was a sutta that illustrates that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it was about a group of devas
[SPEAKER_00]: We're talking to the Buddhas or something and they were... they lived in such a realm where they're all so confined, so packed up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, like, I don't know, thousands of them would stand on... would be like... would take the space of a needle... a needle head.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yet, they have no... no ill will, their minds are immeasurable, and doesn't matter how squeezed they are, basically, they're internally kind of... they're unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then Sariputta said, oh, that's probably because, you know, they maintain, they practice that... in that realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the devas corrected him and said, actually, no, please let him know that it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the practice we made while we were humans.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the human realm,
[SPEAKER_00]: The effort, the little effort that I made, resulted being reborn in these, in these, like, obviously factually better places, where the mind is simply unconstricted, because the lift, little, what might feel like little effort now, little effort in the right direction, obviously, not any effort, but little effort in the right direction, can, as the other suttas say, be like streams of merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you could spend your whole life keeping the five precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: Being generous, being helpful, being kind, and that's like the base sort of threshold of meritorious behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but you still... you wouldn't know whether it will be enough or not, or for how long you will be benefiting from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the Buddha would go and explain, says, but if one develops the right view, cultivates the right view, even for the duration of a finger snap, or the actual jhāna, withdrawal from sensuality, thoroughly, thorough drying up, even just for a finger snap, that's like the streams of immeasurable merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, even you failing to actually, say, get the right view, or become an arahant,
[SPEAKER_00]: Practicing according to the right method that he describes in this sutta will be immeasurably more meritorious than any merit that you do in a mundane sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another kind of encouragement as to, well, even if I fail, my failure is higher than not even trying, basically, in terms of the pure merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's for that sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, kind of, it connects.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's this... the next sutta we want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's Anguttara 557.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a part about the action, but we'll get to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, because these are the... again, these are the five themes that should often be reflected upon a woman or a man, householder or one gone forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, so, no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: No difference in what you gotta... what method you have to follow, what requirements you have to reach and what reflections you have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: What five?
[SPEAKER_00]: A woman or a man, a... a householder, or one gone forth, should reflect that I'm subject to old age, I'm not exempt from old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: A woman or a man, in a householder gone forth, should often reflect I'm subject to illness, I'm not exempt from illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The third one is I'm subject to death, I'm not exempt from death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fourth one is, I must be, and will be, inevitably, parted, separated from everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eh... the fifth, it's, I am the owner of my actions, heir to my actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have actions as my origin, actions as my relative, actions as my resort.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will be the heir of whatever actions, good or bad, that I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we just talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even if you don't necessarily
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you won't be able to recognize the implications of your actions, because you simply don't see the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you can guess, you can have an inkling, but the implications of your actions are kind of infinite in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... but you could know whether your actions are rooted in wholesome intentions, intentions that are aligned with the Noble Eightfold Path,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the wrong intentions, intentions of sensuality, intentions of ill-will, they are not aligned with the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need to wait to confirm the results of your actions, because obviously, you know, your life will run out and the results would have not necessarily been depleted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know that they are rooted in wholesome, if they are rooted in the right intention, you know that nothing bad can come out of them, even in 20 eons time, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the direction is decided in the beginning, on the basis of your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no intention that's rooted in unwholesome, can result in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: No intention rooted in wholesome, can result in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that just remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it's a meritorious, in a sense, aligned with the Noble Eightfold Path, like in terms of the highest merit,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even need to worry about the implications and stuff, because you recognize that the roots of it are rooted in wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if the whole world blames you for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, you want to be celibate, you want to withdraw from sensuality as a lay person, and everybody around you is attacking you for it, and saying that you're...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know... you're mad, you're... it's unnatural, you shouldn't be doing it, and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you don't, yourself, do not see a direct benefit, if you have enough faith, in terms of the, like, practice towards the Sotāpārthi outlined by the Buddha, it will be enough to keep you doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will be meritorious.
[SPEAKER_00]: In and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, factually, the mind, that wild animal, is not being polluted, is not being constricted more, is not being sent down the pathways that would then have this... a lot, kind of, worse repercussions and implications.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when people act out of sensuality, they act out of a constricted context, constricted perspective, reduced perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's pretty much where all of the world's problems come from.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there's that sutta, I think, was it Dighanikā, where the Buddha says it's because of the sensuality that, I don't know, husbands fight with wives, with sons, sons with mothers, sisters, kings in the end, like kings fight with kings and everybody else, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: People resort to sticks, weapons, killing each other, lying, all because of the sensuality, because of their desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: A single reason for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the sutta continues, it says, for the sake of... for the sake of what benefit should a woman, a man, householder, or one gone forth reflect that I'm subject to age, I'm not exempt from old age?
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, beings in the youth are intoxicated with the youth and when they're intoxicated with the youth, they engage in misconduct by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just exactly what I was saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: You already start with a reduced perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already start with a constricted context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because the bigger picture is sort of mystically hidden away from you or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you are ignoring certain aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually the unpleasant ones, such as I'm subject to old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: A young person does not like to think, doesn't want, doesn't see a point in thinking about them getting old and how it will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why don't they see a point?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they're drunk.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're drunk with the youth.
[SPEAKER_00]: They simply refuse to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the Buddha needed to encourage these reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because by making an effort to think those things, like in that kind of personally felt sense, not just abstractly contemplating old age or something, but in that personally felt sense, the Buddha needed to encourage people to do it, because it goes against the grain of your whole being.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes against what you would want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes against the alignment of your desires and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it says,
[SPEAKER_00]: But when one often reflects upon this theme, the intoxication with youth is either completely abandoned or at least diminished.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you are intoxicated because you refuse to think about the obvious nature of your life, of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You refuse to stick to those reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: You refuse to cultivate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You refuse to allow them to kind of sink in and be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you do,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the intoxication of the youth cannot remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be undermined.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be eroded and eventually would evaporate or at least diminish.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the Buddha said it's for the sake of that benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's for the sake of basically sobering up in regard to your life, in regard to the permanence that that implies, ownership and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the next one is...
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when beings are healthy, they're intoxicated with their health.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, they refuse to think about illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: They kind of immediately default back to that automatic conviction that, okay, now that I'm cured, I'll be healthy forever, type of thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you know deep down, of course, I can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will get sick, but I'll deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it comes, I'll be okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just, again, like a carelessness that results on account of being drunk with your current health.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you simply don't care what happens to you in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you refuse to think about the obvious possibility of illness coming at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in and of itself, that intoxication wouldn't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, as the Sutta says, and as anybody honest enough would see, it would be impossible to not engage in misconduct by body, speech and mind, if you're not intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it would be also impossible to not engage in misconduct by body, speech and mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it's not possible to think that you can be intoxicated, but not engage in misconduct by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication automatically leads to misconduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you want it or not, intoxication will imply it, will carry it, will basically manifest it, the misconduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you could be making all the effort you want to police your conduct,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not undermining the intoxications, you're not uprooting anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your misconduct is still there, the framework for it is still there, waiting, and sooner or later things will manifest through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you're gonna do one thing or the other rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, yes, you start with sense restraint and precepts and withdrawal, but it's these reflections that then start to address the roots of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the intoxication with health, intoxication with youth, are removed, well, the great basis for future misconduct, for the possibility of misconduct, is removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are actually uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is the benefit that a woman or man, householder, or one go forth, should reflect, should often reflect on the illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The third one is same about death, but it's the same principles as one should reflect that I am subject to death, I'm not exempt from death, because during their lives, beings are intoxicated with their life, and when they're intoxicated, they engage in misconduct by body, speech, and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this one is kind of probably the most... offers the most contrast.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the most obvious that when you genuinely contemplate death, you immediately, like, kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Undermine all of the desires that you might still have towards anything that's based on life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or at least threaten them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will feel threatened if you actually start contemplating death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's only because there is still intoxication and expectation and assumption of permanence in regard to life.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the intoxication, thinking about death will be the most liberating thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it just reveals the... that which you would have already developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why a householder or a monk should often reflect on these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the next one is
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to possessions, so it's like whether a householder or a monk, the benefit for often reflecting that I must be parted and separated from everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me, is just to kind of undermine that day-to-day negligence, willful ignorance of taking up things, taking up possessions, while if you were to stop
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop a context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will recognize that even things that are yours are not yours, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you... the only time... say... say you borrow something from somebody.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time you would basically believe or start believing that you're an owner is if you forget that it was actually borrowed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if, say, you never knew.
[SPEAKER_00]: You thought it was genuinely yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you discover that, no, you just borrowed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at any point of your usage of the thing that you borrowed, that you know and you make the effort to not forget that it's borrowed, at no point would you then think, oh, I'm the owner, I'm the master of this, because at any time the owner can come and ask for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're still using it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to destroy it or throw it away to prove that it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already fully understood that it's not yours in in its own nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's kind of the nature and that's something like when people
[SPEAKER_00]: I find difficult to understand, like, oh, how is the arahant... how does he operate on a day-to-day basis when, you know, when anatta is fully developed, nothing is his.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he still has perceptions of things and significance of the things and what they can... what those things can be used for, but at no point does he fall back into that view, which he's now incapable of, that he is the owner and those things are, like, solely dependent for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever he engages with, he engages through that third-person sense in a way that this is someone's else.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: Throughout.
[SPEAKER_00]: throughout the duration of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, eh... if you frequently think and recollect that, that even things that are yours, including people, are not yours, cannot be yours, because at any given time they can be taken away, and... and it's unfathomable for you to be even able to, like, see how that will happen, or stop it, or... or be in the way of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just gonna be subjected to it one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about... See, none of these reflections are about
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to think this through and arrive at some sort of resolution.
[SPEAKER_00]: These reflections are not the management of your anxiety, of your fear of illness, of your fear of losing the loved ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are actually supposed to bring it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're supposed to bring it up, because you're willingly choosing to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the benefits of bringing it up is to train your own mind to stop ignoring it, to stop resisting it, and to stop taking it for granted, because that's where the sense of ownership comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can tell, as the, again, like the your commonplace sort of Theravāda instructions, like, ah, you know, practice anatta, nothing is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Electrons are constantly changing, collapses are constantly flowing and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you could be repeating that, parroting that for the rest of your life and no amount of your ownership would have diminished as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the ownership diminishes when that wild animal ceases to be wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that wild animal starts to listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your own citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your own citta cannot take possession of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for that, you need more than just these superficial mantras to repeat to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that, you need these reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that, you need to feel the danger, the fear, the discomfort of the ideas of separation, illness, death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, not just so if I feel this long enough, things will magically fall into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I bring these feelings up because the mind doesn't want to look at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I bring it up, so that the mind learns how to... the animal learns to sit down and calm down in face of these things, and not pressure me and push me and goad me and prod me to go back to sensuality and provide its distraction, so it continues thinking away from the obvious nature of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness, aging, death, separation from everything that's agreeable and dear to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not to, like, torture your mind either,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really the reference point for these reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, the more you do these reflections, the clearer will be... your mind will be outlined as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where the resistance will be coming from, in regard to these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why frequently recollecting this can lead to the right view in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, paired with virtue and the prior withdrawal from everything unwholesome you should have withdrawn, as the previous sutta said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to expect like a perfect contemplation or perfect results of this contemplation right from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to kind of provoke the mind out of that sense of indolence, out of that sense of ignorance, negligence and non-self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's probably going to be felt unpleasantly in the beginning, but again, you're not doing it for the sake of, like, amplifying that discomfort or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, sometimes people might feel, okay, so if I double down and increase this pain of this fear, somehow things will be quicker.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: The measure is the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you reflect these things, on these things,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have maybe some feelings, some resistance come up, and then you leave it there, and try not not sort of get distracted from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as the other suttas say, you want to be furnishing your mind with these perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is looking one way, and that's the way you are showing it these perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It looks like, oh, here's a bit of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, you want to see this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can look at it, but look at it through the contemplation of illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look at it through the contemplation of losing the things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how the mind will then realize that it cannot outrun... that... that... also it will realize that ignorance doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why avijja feeds avijja, as the sutta says, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through ignoring, you genuinely convince yourself that the problem is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's... it's... it's on the level of citta does that already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by frequently recollecting on these things, it will eventually sink down into the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta will understand that even when you ignore stuff, these things are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that belief that your ignorance works, will be diminished.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, it will be completely uprooted, if you stick to these reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even monks were encouraged to contemplate death, contemplate these things, because it's like... like the quickest way to basically teach the mind what really needs to understand, and it's the quickest way towards freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... that's kind of the point, that... through recollecting these things, not for the sake of psychologizing your way out of pain, or... or doubling down, like, through the ascetic, like, bearing of the pain, and just... just bringing more of this context.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Provide, let's say like that, provide a certain discomfort to your mind, and then leave it with it, until it gets used to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't need to be terribly overwhelming, or anything like that, but it needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of resonance needs to be there, and it's not going to be felt like resonance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be felt like dissonance, probably, because, as I said, all the desires and everything else is leaning towards looking away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you've provided long enough, if you reflect on these things long enough, it's not that you will become incapable of forgetting things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, forgetfulness is just the nature of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will be unable to maintain and carry further the belief that forgetfulness exempted you from these contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That connection will be severed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what means, like, avijjā is destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that arahant is constantly thinking about everything all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that even when he forgets, that forgetting happens within his recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollectedness of certain contexts that no forgetfulness can induce any old beliefs of, oh, I'm actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Separated from those implications, those things do not apply to me anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the power of distraction, the power of sensuality, because for as long as that belief, that connection with the vijja exists, then giving in to those directions of distraction, even if you keep telling to yourself, oh, I know this is unbeneficial,
[SPEAKER_00]: On the inside, your mind, your citta, still believes that it does actually, at least for that duration, free you from these pressures of these inevitable contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once that belief is severed, well, your work's pretty much done then.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not be able to return to sensuality, because the sole purpose of the entire sensual domain was to maintain that momentum of that belief that makes you basically feel free from the problems of this fundamental existential nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the benefit of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what's the benefit because of which a woman or a man, householder, one gone false, should reflect that I am the owner of my actions, heir to my actions, have actions as my origin, actions as my relative, actions as my resort.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will be the heir to whatever actions, good or bad, that I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I already said, kind of talked about it in the... when we did the... just now, the previous... the first sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically recognizing that
[SPEAKER_00]: The wholesome or unwholesome or neutral actions are determined by your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that kind of brings the weight of the responsibility on the intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because usually, in the beginning, the weight of the responsibility of one's actions are pretty much on the results of one's actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you know, I'll steal for it, and I'll lie, and I'll feel the weight of it only if I get caught.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how many people operate.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I don't get caught, if I don't obviously harm anybody, it's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see it as a problem and they'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start recognizing that the action begins with your intention, means, oh, you're already incurring a lot of unwholesome, including, like, the actual results of those actions are already felt, even if you don't necessarily see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those results are felt on the level of that wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I often say, as I said in those previous talks as well, everything might feel fine, even for people that don't keep the precepts, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that they're like unhappy or something because of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that they're going to pay a higher price and they're already paying it without realizing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like when the wild animal is allowed the wilderness, it's allowed to do what he wants, it's not being tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically increasing its capacity for wilderness, its capacity for being irrational and crazy and wild and prone to passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, when that animal turns around and bites you, which it will, when illness happens, when you lose... inevitably has to happen, it will bite you a lot harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the state of the mind, of an untrained mind, it's not a neutral, it's not like a static thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, this is untrained and it's... no, it grows and it knows no limits.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the time comes, when that mind doesn't get what it wants, it will turn against you and it will bite you a lot harder, a lot more viciously.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will cause a lot more damage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the mind, let's say, was significantly tamed and still turns around and starts blaming you for something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: I keep telling to people, even when, you know, when they get... when they're caught up in these mental patterns of self-loathing and blame and it's just with all this force and power for years and they can't get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the reason why.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your mind has no respect for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take that away, no amount of your traumas and stuff from the past, and the mind trying to revolve around it, can hit you as hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're taking away the sail from its wind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sail from its wind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wind from its sail.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a static thing, just like black or white.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like your actions matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you feeding the wilderness, the craziness of the animal, or are you reducing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although it still hasn't turned around to bite you, the fact is that you're cultivating the wilderness of the animal, means you're already basically deciding what type of bite it will be when it happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, the results of your actions are already being developed there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even without anything obviously palpable and so on, at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's important to always, like, I'm the owner of my actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I... they cannot go on to anybody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will remain bound with me and this mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no third option there, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no second option in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why these reflections are on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reflection about action and the ownership and the roots of it, which is your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they're on the level of contemplating sickness, aging, death, separation and all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, says the the noble disciple, reflects thus, I'm not the only one who is subject to old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, see, you reflect like this, the way we described it, it will eventually, as I said, outline your mind more and more simply through that sheer gratuitous resistance of the mind in regard to these contemplations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eh... that's... that's pretty much what sotāpatti will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you see your mind that animal clearly, when the...
[SPEAKER_00]: A certain layer of identification with it is abolished through that seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, through perpetually not seeing the animal, through habitually not seeing the extent, the outlines, the nimittas of your mind, that's the ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: The result of that is ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ātavāda is not your theoretical conviction that I am self and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the result
[SPEAKER_00]: of an underlying ignorance, looking past and non-recognition of what the citta is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you would have been outlining it through precepts, restraint and these recollections frequently dwelled upon, the citta will be seen and then, whether you want or not, you will be unable to identify with it and assume yourself as some sort of external owner to the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, attavāda will be gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the noble disciple, once he's kind of cultivated and established in these recollections, will then also know that I'm not... and will be able to remind himself as well, I'm not the only one who is subject to old age, exempt from old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: All beings that come and go, that arise and pass away, they undergo the same, basically, nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're subject to old age, rebirth and birth old age and not exempt from old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subject to old age and non-exempt from old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he will often reflect on this theme.
[SPEAKER_00]: The path is generated even clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: He pursues it, develops it and cultivates it and then all the facts will be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is like a condensed way
[SPEAKER_00]: See, like, you would have contemplated enough that you're subject to old age.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind would have been outlined and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, within that, say you would have abandoned ātavāda, you are a sotāpanna, but within that, there is still that sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: That still lingers through some perversion of perception in regard to the ownership, in regard to permanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not on the scale of a pūtugena, it's not on the extent of a pūtugena's mind, who doesn't see any of it, so he's like really subjected to the whole thing, but there is still remnants, the residues.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the suttas say, it's like, you know, pūtugena would have been stuck with a poison arrow, that's still like emitting poison into the wound,
[SPEAKER_00]: But a noble disciple would have had arrow pulled out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is still now the residual poison left.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, he needs to follow a certain diet, anoint the wound, clean it, until that's gone as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's secondary infections and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what these recollections say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the path will be generated in a sotāpanna, the path that he knows,
[SPEAKER_00]: will be highlighted if he keeps reminding himself of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is... like, again, even... even to the extent that I understood and to the extent that I do have a conceit of I am separate from this person or that person, well, to that extent, you kind of recognize, well, but this I am, that might feel separate to that subtler extent, not like a putugenous level of conceit, but even that cannot be exempted from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that cannot not partake in the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, it's just practicing what Adi Sutta says a noble disciple should practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, not for me, not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he reminds himself through these four or five aspects of sickness, aging, death, losing things that you're connected with and that you are the owner of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not the only one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not the only one subject to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not the only one who must be parted and separated from everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: All beings that come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no exception, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even, not even, like, in terms of the human realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just in any realm, in any shape or form, this is, like, inescapable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means any lingering conceit of I am, that to that extent, I might be separate a little bit for a period of time, you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that's included in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what a noble disciple wants to be practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including the sense of conceit, the little desires that he still has left, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Re-including them into this context until it fully permeates all of the layers that are there that need to be permeated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why then, all the fetters will eventually be abandoned and the underlying tendency completely uprooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, arahantship and complete freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sutta finishes with these verses saying that warlings, putujanas, are subject to illness, old age, death, and are disgusted by other people who exist in accordance with their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they feel, like, quite... to an irrational degree, in a sense, to, like, a degree of madness, they feel separated from the obvious things that they see others go through, and they feel disgusted with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how far gone the putujanas are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how... how exempt from those things they feel, that actually feel justified in their disgust of that which is, like, they're partaking in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, a noble disciple wouldn't be going that far, but then he should remind himself even further that even the slightest disgust with what I perceive in others, I must re-include myself in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, until there is no conceit left, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I were to become disgusted with beings who have such a nature, that would not be proper.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would not be aligned with the path, basically, since I too have the same nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha says, while I was dwelling this, having known the state without acquisitions, without ownership, he overcome all intoxications.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intoxication with health, youth, life, and having seen security in renunciation, means security in giving up sensual desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sīla rose in me and I clearly saw nibbāna and recognized that he's incapable of indulging in sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You frequently recollect these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those cover-ups that serve as maintenance of the belief in your avijjā will become redundant, because you would have destroyed the belief in your avijjā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I ignore this or not, the context remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of what I'm subjected to remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the whole purpose of sensuality is removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it says, like, once you clearly understood that, he recognized that he's incapable of indulging in sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the reason for them is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Relying on this spiritual life, never will I turn back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that concludes, pretty much, these two suttas.